What's that now, don't like the cold?
Can't stay in today.
We have a ritual to perform you and I.
[gurgling]
Here.
Wear this.
It belonged to my daughter.
Good.
Today I speak your name girl.
But will the Goddess speak it back?
Normally it would be the mother who declares...
...if you had one.
The whole village would attend
and Matriarchs perform the ritual.
But we are outcasts.
Even so, we keep the tribe's rituals.
Otherwise we might become like the faithless
Old Ones
who turned their backs on the Goddess.
But their wickedness doomed them.
To us, were left the splendours of creation.
Beasts of air, water, earth...
...and steel.
[roaring]
It is one thing to hunt a beast,
another to hunt a machine.
You must be humble and respect their power.
I will teach you this, one day.
High Matriarch Teersa.
What is she doing here?
Does she mean to forbid the ritual?
No, no, no, off your knees.
It's nearly time.
And yes, you may speak to me.
You came to bless the naming?
Have not six months gone by
since we entrusted her to you?
But we are outcasts.
You by choice, and she...
...well...
I am a High Matriarch Rost.
I bless whom I choose.
Then you honour us?
Yes, yes, now go, and be ready to declare.
Go!
All-Mother this child needs a name by which
to know her.
That your love may warm her life
as the rising sun warms all the earth.
Speak her name!
ALOY!
[echoes] aloy … aloy … aloy
And so her name is blessed.
Stop this at once!
What have you done?
I've blessed the naming of a child.
Stubborn woman, you call that curse a child?
What did she tell you about its birth Outcast?
Answer!
I've done only what you asked.
To raise it yes.
We said nothing of love.
Enough!
And you, blessing its name like it was one
of the Nora, one of the tribe!
I know my duty to them, and to you.
I'm here.
And wherever you go I will follow.
[offscreen] Aloy! Aloy!
Ooh, that's a lot of berries.
You're quite the gatherer aren't you little
Bast?
Now go and see if you can find some more,
hmm?
Well done, that's a good boy.
Children, come with me.
She's an outcast, to be shunned.
Oh, come on… there.
[cries]
[grunting]
[coughing]
Rost!
Down here!
He won't hear me.
Some kind of cave?
Ugh, there are rats down here.
Looks tight, but I can get through.
This must be a ruin of the Metal World.
One of the old places.
Rost said never go in places like this.
But I have to find a way out.
There's something up ahead.
What's that?
A dead person!
There's something shiny there?
Oh!
Lights!
Everywhere!
How does it do this?
A metal door, closed.
Maybe this device I've found can help?
More lights!
A shape, its connected to the door somehow.
It changed colour.
The door changed colour too!
It did it!
What's that?
It's got a device, like the one I found.
You think I want it this way? ->
It's the best I can do.
He's right behind you.
Hi!
Happy birthday Isaac!
Daddy sure does love his little big man!
Look, Daddy can't be there with you and Mom
but we can still have a party, right?
Sure we can!
Show me!
Show me again!
…I can do.
He's right behind you.
Hi!
Happy birthday Isaac!
Daddy sure does love his little big man!
Look, Daddy can't be there with you and Mom
but we can still have a party, right?
Sure we can!
"Happy birthday Isaac."
"Daddy sure does love his little big man."
I saw them lining up in the community room
like cattle in a slaughterhouse,
but smiling at each other
Chana handing out meds like being alive
is some kind of... pain to be eased
Well, not me.
I don't want to go quiet.
I don't want to trail off.
I want a period at the end
of my life sentence,
not an ellipsis.
Hell, an exclamation mark.
So if that upsets whoever finds this, too
bad.
I don't owe anyone anything anymore.
[gunshot]
Well happy new year, dear diary.
Can you believe we actually celebrated last
night?
Well, we did.
Kind of.
Director Evans invited everyone to gather
in the community room.
Don't know where she got the party hats.
That was a ghoulish touch.
So there we sit,
watching the clock tick down to midnight,
and I'm thinking am I the only one here
who gets the symbolism of this?
Might've been worth it if Skylar
had gotten drunk again,
but I seem to be a mistake
she doesn't want to repeat.
Why did they die here?
What happened to them?
…and pray for us sinners now
and at the hour of our debt.
I mean death.
Sorry.
It's been a while and these meds
Chana gave us are really something.
So.
Okay.
From the top, kids.
Hail Mary, full of grace...
And maybe that's all I need, you know?
That moment the door opened
and you were standing there,
wearing that retro-weave dress
and the way you smiled.
I had to look away or you were going to see
on my face
What had just...
…blossomed inside me, you know?
It was just an instant, but I knew.
I knew we'd be forever.
"The earth shall soon dissolve like snow"
"The sun forbear to shine"
"But God, who called me here below"
"Will be forever mine"
And Machu Picchu.
Always wanted to see that.
Never did.
Why didn't I go with Owen when he asked?
Stupid.
I should have gone.
Well.
I mean, seriously,
"Record our thoughts for posterity"?
Great idea, Director Evans.
Like I haven't done enough for posterity already?
Like I wouldn't be here like this if not for
posterity?
I'm done with posterity.
Posterity can go f…
[in the distance]
Aloy! Aloy!
Are you down there?
He found me!
Rost found me.
Down here, I'm coming, I'm coming.
All-Mother be praised!
Come girl, take my hand.
You don't belong down there, come.
Such places are forbidden Aloy.
I fell in.
They are of the Metal World.
What is that on your face?
Nothing.
Did you find it down there?
No.
Give it to me.
Aloy, such things are dangerous.
No!
Well, if you are going to go sneaking away
from home
you need to know how to survive in the wild.
Come Aloy, home now.
Starting tomorrow you will learn to hunt.
All these shapes what do they mean?
Take your bow.
"Bow"?
And enough muttering to that plaything.
We descend to the valley now.
Follow.
The wilds can be dangerous, Aloy.
You will need to stay close and do as I say.
I know.
Now, you're still scratched up
from that fall you took yesterday.
So let's start there.
Take this medicine pouch.
I'll show you how to fill it.
You see this plant over here?
It's called "salvebrush".
Come, gather its berries in your pouch.
Good, now eat the berries.
Bleah!
They may taste bitter
but they can save your life.
Always keep your pouch full
of medicinal berries, flowers, and plants.
Where are we?
This valley is just a part of All-Mother's
Embrace.
"Embrace"
The Nora Tribe watches these lands
and keeps out the most dangerous machines.
Usually.
Further downriver we'll find a herd of machines
and I will teach you how to hunt.
Are they dangerous?
All machines are dangerous, Aloy.
Their power must be respected.
But I will be beside you.
Aloy, a machine is coming.
Crouch and follow me into the tall grass.
There.
Now stay low.
Little ones!
No, Aloy.
Such machines are called Watchers.
You must learn to avoid their gaze
if you are to survive in the wilds.
I will show you.
Listen closely, and do as I do.
Stay still and wait for it to pass.
Now keep low and follow me
across the trail to that tall grass.
Ho, another one, let it pass.
Come, back this way.
The slower you move, the quieter you will
be.
And crouched walking is quieter than upright.
Wait for it.
That's the last of them.
Let's move on.
You did well, they didn't see or hear you.
Now stay close, that herd should be just ahead.
Who's that?
Ignore him.
But why is he up there?
He's smiling at us!
[offscreen]
Teb, get back where you belong.
Teb! Where are you?
Ignore him.
We are outcasts and he is of the tribe.
Maybe he doesn't like the tribe?
Then he is a fool.
Come now, let's find that herd.
Follow.
There, see them?
These are called Striders.
HA! GIT!
Why'd you chase them off?
To show you how some machines startle easily
if they detect you, and run away.
They're best approached by stealth.
Don't worry, we'll catch up with them
further down the valley, you'll see.
Now, I want you to find some rocks
that fit the cup of your hand.
Why?
Do as I say Aloy and gather the rocks.
I will show you how to use them.
Good, that's it.
Those will do.
Follow.
There's the herd.
Alright, it's time to throw some rocks.
But rocks can't hurt machines, right?
No, but they can distract them.
Draw them into traps.
Like that Watcher over there.
They must be dealt with or it will
warn the herd
and send them running before we get in range.
Warn them? How?
The machines speak to each other, Aloy.
Unless they are first silenced.
Now you stay here on the ridge.
On my signal, throw rocks
and draw the Watcher over to me.
Wait for my signal.
Aloy!
Throw a rock near me.
There.
Come girl, it's safe now.
Harvest the kill so I can teach you
how to make arrows.
Good.
Now, gather stalks of Ridge-Wood
from the plants over there.
Use the stalks as arrow shafts
and metal shards for arrow heads.
Good.
You'll never run out of arrows
if you know how to craft what you need.
Let's put those arrows to use.
Follow.
Here. Stay low in the grass and be quiet.
It's time to make your first kill, Aloy.
Strider.
One of the weaker machines.
But even a weak machine can
kill a hunter if she's careless.
You must study your prey.
It's hide is thick but there are spots
where it is vulnerable, like its eye.
Can you guess another?
The canister on its back.
Is that a weakness?
Yes, how did you guess that?
The device, it showed me.
That plaything?
Stop playing games.
Now, take down that Strider.
Target the eye or the canister.
And if it charges,
be ready to roll out of the way.
Keep firing!
Again!
You did well today but you have much to learn.
Tomorrow we train again.
[yelling] →
What was that?
That boy, the one running the Brave Trails.
Follow Aloy, quick!
[grunting]
[scream]
I can do nothing.
It is only a matter of time before the machines
find that boy and kick him to death.
But if I shoot it would cause
a stampede and trample him.
But I can see the paths they take.
Stop telling stories.
I'm not, I can sneak through!
You will not.
Aloy!
I need to move slowly and quietly
so I can sneak past them.
Can't let them see me.
Got to be careful.
I need to see their paths.
Almost there.
There he is!
Hey!
What?
How … how is this …?
Ssh!
Follow me.
How do you know to avoid them?
How are you doing this?
How is this possible?
So it is no plaything.
Wait.
All-Mother bless that girl.
Bless you both.
Boy!
She saved me.
I just want to…
← BOY!
Seal your lips!
They are outcasts both.
And she is motherless.
Come now!
Back to Mother's Heart.
That boy should not have spoken to us.
It's against tribal law.
We'll go home now.
Follow.
I know the way!
"Seal your lips boy … seal your lips"
Aah!
Stay away No Mother!
[offscreen]
Children, away from there!
Back to picking berries.
You're bleeding.
Let me have a look.
Here, hold still, I'll get it.
Why?
Ssh!
Why am I an outcast?
Aloy, this is not the time.
Who was my mother?
Aloy, I've told you before
that's not for us to know.
You were just a newborn when
the Matriarchs brought you to me.
So the Matriarchs they know?
It's not so simple!
But they know?
Aloy, we are outcasts.
So how do I make them tell me?
The Matriarchs?
There is a way, perhaps.
So tell me!
It would be dangerous.
How?
It would take years of training.
I don't care!
How do I do it?
Tell me!
The Proving.
The tribe's rite of passage held every year.
Those who pass become Braves.
But to the one who wins
the Matriarchs grant a boon.
A boon?
Yes, whatever the winner wants.
Then I'll do it.
Whatever it takes.
I'll win the Proving.
I see.
We'd best get started then.
Your training will be hard
and it will take years.
Start training?
Yes!
Follow!